Guide to the Walter Prichard Eaton Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Walter Prichard Eaton papers
1894-1948
MS 190
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3.25
(7 boxes)
The papers consist largely of short stories, reviews, criticism, notes, and a small quantity of correspondence.
Eaton, Walter Prichard, 1878-1957
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of F. C. Canfield, 1959; and transferred from the Frank McMullan Papers, 1988.
Biographical / Historical
Walter P. Eaton: worked in the drama department, New York Tribune, 1902-1907; drama critic, New York Sun, 1907-1908; drama critic, American Magazine, 1909-1918; professor of playwriting, Yale University, 1933-1947; free-lance drama and theater critic; author.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist largely of short stories, reviews, criticism, notes, and a small quantity of correspondence.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged by accession.
Literature -- History and criticism; Theater; Authors; Educators; Eaton, Walter Prichard, 1878-1957; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Department of Drama
- Inventory, 1912-1948; 2.25 linear feet (6 boxes)
  - Letters
    - 5 letters from WPE to Marshall Buick (Box 1)
    - A.W.Barmby to WPE, Apr 14,1922 (Box 1)
    - M.M.Meloney to A.W.Barmby, Apr 12,1922 (concerns WPE) (Box 1)
    - H.E.Stevens to WPE, Apr 11,1922 (Box 1)
    - F.M.Holly to WPE. Sept 14,1914 (Box 1)
    - Ellery Sedgwick to WPE, Dec 18,1912 (Box 1)
    - Ted Weeks to WPE, Jun 26,1948 (Box 1)
    - Lara Owen to WPE, Feb 15,? (Box 1)
    - T.K. Stewart to WPE, May 6, 7, 1927 (Box 1)
    - R.B. Carter to WPE, Aug 25, 1964 (Box 1)
    - unidentified to WPE, Jul 13, 1944 (Box 1)
  - Reviews by WPE
    - The Confessions of a Dealer by Thomas Rohen (Box 1)
    - The Decline of Cussing by H.L.Mencken - an article on American profanity in American Speech Autobiography by James Hackett (Box 1)
    - The Old World House; Its Furniture and Decoration by Herbert Cescinsky (Box 1)
    - The Dreamer Delivered-Epoch, the Life of Steele MacKaye by Percy MacKaye (Box 1)
    - Annals of the New York Stage by George C.D. Odell (Box 1)
    - The Modern Ibsen - an Interpretation by Herman Weigand (Box 1)
    - Vocabularios Causiere: But - is it Art? by Percy Hammond (Box 1)
    - The Quest of the Antique by Mrs. Willoughy Hodgson (Box 1)
    - The Ladies' Home Journal One Act Plays (Box 1)
    - George Henry Becker by E.S.Bradley (Box 1)
    - Restoration Drama - 1926 Model by John Upton (Box 1)
    - One Act Plays for Young Folks edited by M.A.Jagendorf Criticism (Box 1)
  - Criticism
    - The Amateur-Revolt in Our Theater (Box 1)
    - What is a Moral Play? (Box 1)
    - New Poetry and the Lingering Line (Box 1)
    - Essays of Our Own Elia -- On Modern Dance Music (Box 1)
    - The Boy and the Book (3 copies: 2 complete, 1 incomplete) (Box 1)
    - Critics (Box 1)
    - Notes for a Ph.D. Thesis (Box 1)
    - Books for Boys (Box 1)
    - paper on American newspapers (Box 1)
    - paper on the problem of the Christian Church in modern society Fata Morgana -- critical questions and comments asked Lines in the Cambridge Revised Bible (Box 1)
  - Papers about individuals
    - Agnes Booth (Box 1)
    - Frederick Bartlett Conway (Box 1)
    - James Henry Hackett (Box 1)
    - James Keteltas Hackett (Box 1)
    - James A. Hearne (Box 1)
    - Francesca Romania Magdelena Jaranshek (Box 1)
    - Thomas Wallace] Keene (Box 1)
    - Francis Ann Kemble (Mrs. Pierce Butler) (Box 1)
    - Henry Thoreau (Box 1)
    - Artemus Ward (Box 1)
    - Percival Wilde (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous
    - The English Drama on the Stage, Preface (Box 1)
    - 2 "Forewords" (both are different) (Box 1)
    - 1 pocket notebook (Box 1)
    - Notes for address or lecture (5 diff. subjects) (Box 1)
    - 2 papers from students with WPE's comments (Box 1)
    - Development of an Aspect of Unitary Christianity - presented to WPE with the compliments of the author, Nelson J. Springer (Box 1)
    - Paper on Richard Mansfield, Jr., and other actors (Box 1)
    - Three photographs of WPE (Box 1)
    - Certificate: "The First Chevrolet Television Award" (Box 1)
    - The Useless Memories of Prentice Piper (592 pages complete) (Box 2)
    - Sky Line Camps (113 pages, complete) (Box 2)
    - A Road Away From Rome: Why I Live in the Country (Box 2)
    - Hawkeye's Roommate - A Story of Hampshire School (Box 3)
    - Lord of the Wilderness (Box 3)
    - Lake Chilan (incomplete: pps 114-393 present) (Box 3)
  - Short Stories
    - To Whom Does the Future Belong (Box 3)
    - The Twilight of the White Pines (Box 3)
    - The Clouds on Cannon (15 pps typed) (Box 3)
    - On Groaning at Puns (Box 3)
    - The Haunt of the Golden Hemlock (Box 3)
    - Putterin' 'Round the Garden (Box 3)
    - The Garden I Dream of (Box 3)
    - The Bird House Stories - The Chickadee (Box 3)
    - Junk, Deluxe (Box 3)
    - $10 a Hole for the Heathen (Box 3)
  - Short Stories
    - A Critic's Memories (Box 4)
    - What College Did to Me (Box 4)
    - The Pampered Fledgling (Box 4)
    - Winter Bon Fire (Box 4)
    - "The Better Things of Life" (Box 4)
    - English as She Wasn't Taught (Box 4)
    - The Boy Grows Up (Box 4)
    - The Ideal Golf Course (Box 4)
    - Musings at Myopia (Box 4)
    - Iron Deer (Box 4)
    - A Procrastinated Christmas (Box 4)
    - Tell Me Next Wednesday (Box 4)
    - Two in the Town (Box 4)
    - First Nights (Box 4)
    - The Rights of Small Notions - A Peep from the Averave Man (Box 4)
    - On Changing Human Nature (Box 4)
    - The Pleasing Land of Drowsy-head (Box 4)
    - White Christmas (Box 4)
    - Andover Sesquicentennial - May 1928 (an address or poem) (Box 4)
    - Woman's Place is the Home Green (Box 4)
    - If Motor Cars Could Talk (Box 4)
    - The Man etc. (Box 4)
    - The Puppy Rug (24 pps typed) (Box 4)
    - The Drone that Played Gadfly (Box 4)
    - Little Old Eliza (Box 4)
    - The Little God in the Square (16 pps typed) (Box 4)
    - Concentrate-and Be a Crab (Box 4)
    - The Educated Man and the Practical Theater (Yale Phi Betta Kappa - Dec 15,1911) (Box 4)
    - He Understood Women (Box 4)
    - Little Old Blam (2 copies; one typed, the other handwritten) (Box 4)
    - A Dabble in Iniquity (Box 4)
    - Main 12 - Ring 3 (Box 4)
    - A Return Engagement (Box 4)
    - The Auction Hounds (Box 4)
    - The Bauble -- An Academic Drama (Box 4)
    - Holding Up the Mirror to Art (Box 4)
    - The Antique Rug (Box 4)
    - Creative Youth (Box 4)
    - The Man Broadway Forgot (16 pps) (Box 4)
    - The Meadow Larks (Box 4)
    - The Song of the Sirens (Box 4)
    - A Downcast Uplifter (Box 4)
  - Short Stories
    - Imaginary Conversations-Shakespeare and J.M.Barrie (Box 5)
    - That Smoky Fireplace (Box 5)
    - Come into the Kitchen (Box 5)
    - Pity the Middle- Aged (Box 5)
    - The Whip-poor-will (Box 5)
    - 52 Weeks a Year (Box 5)
    - On Being Cheerful Before Breakfast (Box 5)
    - Wild Strawberries (Box 5)
    - "Thou Waitest Late and Com'st Alone" (Box 5)
    - "On Going to Some Other Place" (Box 5)
    - Boughs in the Snow (Box 5)
    - Spring Jewells [sic] (Box 5)
    - Lament for Susie (Susie is a stove) (Box 5)
    - Shaving Mugs (Box 5)
    - Ain't Science Wonderful (Box 5)
    - Caves (Box 5)
    - A Dangling Shovel (Box 5)
    - Don't Go Home (Box 5)
    - Happiness in Creases (Box 5)
    - Rhubarb and Cream (Box 5)
    - The Forgotten Boy (Box 5)
    - Deer Week (Box 5)
    - Scenery vs. Sound (Box 5)
    - Hot Caps (Box 5)
    - Chucks (Box 5)
    - The Pittsfield Panther (Box 5)
    - Lights in the Larkspur (Box 5)
    - Sanctuary (Box 5)
    - Under the Greenwood Tree (Box 5)
    - Friendly with the Sky (Box 5)
    - Chrystal Cloud (Box 5)
  - The Duck Series
    - Dodo Duck's Tea Party (Box 5)
    - Adventures of the Duck Family - How the Little Duck Lost His Squeak (25 pps; also 28 p. variant: plus one page fragment of another copy) (Box 5)
    - Roffles-Penrod letter/ Penrod seems to be the little duck mentioned in the "squeak" story. Roffles is an enigma. (Box 5)
  - Plays
    - Grandma -Old Style (Box 5)
    - One of our Old Families (notes on the play only; no dialogue) (Box 5)
    - Real Realism (a three page short to illustrate the "raw slice of life") (Box 5)
    - Act I, Act II (two untitled acts belonging to the same play, but apparently not to One of our Old Families ) (Box 5)
    - Eighty-four untitled manuscripts (Box 5)
    - Six incomplete manuscripts (Box 5)
    - Twenty-six incomplete manuscripts (Box 6)
- Additional Material, (1894-1947); Accession 1988-M-067; 0.5; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Addition inventory by Susan Brady 1988 February
  Transferred from the Frank McMullan Papers, 1988, Feb 11
  This material has been described according to a list found with the material. The list (in folder 1) may have been created by Eaton, Eaton's wife, or Frank McMullan. Some untitled articles and lectures were assigned titles by the creator of the list; they are identified in the following listing by an asterisk (*).
  - List of Walter P. Eaton Papers, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Lectures
    - "Man's Need of Drama", undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "Theater as a Business"*, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "Value of Theater from an Ethical Point of View"*, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "Acting", undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "American Drama", undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "Shakespeare in Schools"*, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "Radio Interview"*, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "The Drama as Life's Looking Glass", undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "The Nature and Changing Forms of Drama", undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "The Bondage of the Box Office"*, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "The American Drama-an Infant Industry", undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "On Going to the Theater", 1906 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "Finding the Author through Criticism"*, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Lecture on Realism" (I)*, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Lecture on Realism" (II)*, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Lecture on Realism" (III)*, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Where is American Drama Going?", undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Our Changing Drama", undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Mechanical Substitutes for Literature in the Theater"*, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Who Are the Puritans?", undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Notebooks
    - Drama 9, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "What Do We Know about Acting?", undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Magazine Clippings (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "Some Ideas on Stage Decoration" by Ellen Terry, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "The Marvel of Mary Anderson" by T. Edgar Pemberton, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "The Mission Play of California" by Henry Van Dyke, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "Some Pupils of Liszt" by Albert Morris Bagby, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "Madame Modjeska" by J. Ranken Bagby, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "The History and Progress of the Ballet" by Rosita Mauri, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "A Four-hundred-Year Old Cottage in Kent, Where Ellen Terry Lives in the Summertime", undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "Vision the Source of Achievement" by Mary Fanton Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "Leaves from the Autobiography of Salvini", undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "Pictorial Successes of Mr. Irving's 'Faust'" by Joseph and Elizabeth Pennell, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "The Acting in Mr. Irving's 'Faust'", undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "The Chinese Theater" by Henry Burden McDowell, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "The Real Edwin Booth-His Letters", 1894 (Box 1, Folder 3)